Inventory of the Victor Gollancz Ltd. miscellaneous records
Hoover Institution Archives
Victor Gollancz Ltd. miscellaneous records
1962-1999
2015C18
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box (0.4 linear feet)
Correspondence and publication agreements relating to publication of an English-language edition of the novel One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich by Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn.
Victor Gollancz Ltd..
Access
The collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2015.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Historical Note
Victor Gollancz Ltd. was a major British book publishing house founded in 1927 by Victor Gollancz (1893-1967) and acquired by Houghton Mifflin in 1989. The company was the original publisher for a number of well-known authors, including George Orwell, Hilde Meisel, and Alfred Ayer.
Scope and Content of Collection
The Victor Gollancz Ltd. miscellaneous records contain correspondence and publication agreements relating to the publication of Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn’s One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich.
The correspondence consists of incoming and outgoing letters between publishers in Russia, Scotland, New Zealand, Australia, the United Kingdom, and the United States regarding royalty payments for publications, copyright permissions for educational use, and authorization for extracting certain passages. Correspondents include Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn, Victor Gollancz, Ralph Parker, and James MacGibbon.
The collection also includes legal contracts covering expected payments and guidelines for the republishing of One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich. Of particular note are the original contract and early correspondence about securing the first English language publication of the work, as well as the last reversion of rights, which gave legal ownership of the title back to Solzhenitsyn.
Solzhenit͡syn, Aleksandr Isaevich, 1918-2008.; Dissenters--Soviet Union.; Russian literature.
- Agreements, 1962, 1979
  - Translation, 1962 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Press, 1979 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Correspondence, 1962-1999
  - 1962-1963 (Box-folder 1: 3-4)
  - 1962-1980 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - 1963 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - 1963-1964 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - 1965, 1988-1999 (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - 1972 (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - 1980 (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - 1980-1983 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - 1980-1988 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - 1999 (Box-folder 1: 13)
    Scope and Contents note
    Includes reversion of rights agreement returning all legal publishing rights to Solzhenitsyn.